United Federal Workers Records 5653
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
United Federal Workers Records
1937-1952
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
United Federal Workers
5653
0.5 cubic feet
This collection consists of clippings from the United Public Workers (UPW) National Convention, 1948; publications from the UPWA, its predecessor union, and other labor organizations; a copy of the Local #203 United Federal Workers of America Shop Stewards guide book; and newspaper clippings from February and March 1946.
0.5 linear ft.
Records (documents).
5685204
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the activities of the United Public Workers union.
Of particular note in this collection are the anti-discrimination activities that the union engaged in. Specifically, the union was focused on ending Jim Crow segregation in federal employments in Washignton DC. The campaign to de-segregate the engravers of the Deptment of the Treasury is a major focus of the collection. Also included are the attempts to de-segregate worknin and living conditions for federal workers in the Panama Canal Zone after President Truman's Executive Order 9980, issued on July 26, 1948, mandating fair employment practices in the federal workforce.
Also present are clippings and other materials docuementing the union's response to the rise of anti-communist feelings in the United States and the associated legislation that targeted labor organizations during the rise of McCarthyism in the late 1940s and early 1950s.
Related Materials
Related Collections:
5962: Milton Kelenson Papers
5962 P: Milton Kelenson Photographs
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives 227 Ives Hall Tower Road Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheelref@cornell.edu https://catherwood.library.cornell.edu/kheel/
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, July 18, 2005
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 25, 2019
Labor unions; African-Americans -- Civil rights -- United States; Civil rights movements; Discrimination in employment; United Federal Workers of America
5685204
- UFW and UPW campaigns for better wages for federal and D.C. employees, 1943-1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  This folder contains records documenting various campaigns run by the UFW and the UPW to improve wages for workers in the Washignton D.C. area. The majority of the materials are about public school teachers and matrons (school nurses), but there are also materials about public library workers and elevator operators.
- UPW reaction to President Truman's anti-discrimination Executive Order 9980, July 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  This folder contains the text of President Truman's EO 9980 (July 26, 1948) that established fair hiring practices in the federal workforce and petitions from the UPW to ask for the formation of a committee to enforce the terms of the executive order
- Letter re UPW death benefit fund, June 24,1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Letter to all UPW local financial secretaries
- Flyers for UPW campaigns for better wages and working conditions, circa 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- UPW campaign against discrimination at the Treasury Department's Bureau of Engraving, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- UPW campaign against discrimination at the Treasury Department's Bureau of Engraving, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- UPW campaign against discrimination at the Treasury Department's Bureau of Engraving, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- UPW campaign against discrimination at the Treasury Department's Bureau of Engraving, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "D.C. Federal Reporter" (vol. 1, nos. 1 - 4) published by the D.C. Locals of the UPW, July 1946 - October 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Clippings - United Public Workers (UPW-CIO) National Convention, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  This folder contains clippings documenting the 1948 convention of the UPW and various actions it took to try and address the rising anti-communist sentiment, especially in the provisions of the Taft-Hartley Act. The clippings are from various newspapers.
- United Public Workers of America (CIO) Constitution (as revised in convention, May 1948) (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Summary of proceedings, second biennial convention, United Public Workers of America, May 17 - 20, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Clippings re expulsion of leftist unions from the CIO, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Local 203 United Federal Workers of America Shop Stewards guide book, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  This folder contians a guide book for shop stewards. This booklet was printed by the union for shop stewards to use for their reference and in the course of taking three training classes to prepare them for their roles. The booklets were individually numbered and ke[t track of by the union. The contents include text for the three classes and five appendices that contain a copy of Local 203's constitution, information on the history of the U.S. civil service, the Hatch Act, the federal wage scale, and post-World War II reconversion efforts.
- Publications of the United Federal Workers of America (1 of 2), 1937-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Publications of the United Federal Workers of America (2 of 2), 1937-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Newspaper Clippings, February 1946 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Newspaper Clippings, March 1946 (Box 1, Folder 18)